A Guide to the Rockefeller Foundation records, officers' diaries, RG 12, A-E FA391
Rockefeller Archive Center
- DeVinney, Leland C.
  - 1964 October 1-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 194 pages (Reel M Dev 6, Frame 1, Box 122)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney attended multiple conferences including the Meeting on Summer Institute for College Teachers organized by Education Services Inc., a luncheon meeting of the Foundations Group to talk about responsible philanthropy in America. He also attended a meeting called by the Ad Hoc Committee of American Council Education hosted at the Rockefeller Institute to make a new organization that parallels Educational Services Inc., and accepts direct responsibility for planning; sponsoring administering and raising funds for a wide range of projects to improve African American education in the South. A lengthy summary of the Puerto Rico Conference on the Implications of Universal Higher Education is included and details how to improve higher education in Puerto Rico. DeVinney also visits Tougaloo College in Mississippi and Tulane University in New Orleans in support of Black education.
    Diaries; United States; Social sciences; Education; Black studies
  - 1965 January 4-May 28, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 272 pages (Box 122, Reel M Dev 6, Frame 194)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits Hampton Institute, a historically Black college to assess academic programs and determine its current grant funding allocations. He attends the Conference on William C. Archie's proposal for foundation support of tax-supported Black colleges in North Carolina. The proposal is to set up a special freshman-year program designed to bridge the academic gap and make up for deficiencies in high school. DeVinney also visits the Friends Neighborhood Guild in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania as well as attends the Meetings of the Population Association of America.
    Diaries; Black studies; Population; Education; United States; Social sciences
  - 1965 June 1-December 30, DeVinney, Leland C.; Rockefeller Foundation; 297 pages (Box 122, Reel M Dev 6, Frame 467)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney takes a trip to visit various colleges that have programs to bridge the academic gap for underprivileged and minority students as incoming freshman. He attends the International Conference on Family Planning Programs, the Invitational Conference on Testing Problems and the Annual Meeting of the Southern Regional Council. DeVinney also visits the Office of Economic Opportunity (OEO) and the Office of Education to discuss the substantial government funding for educational and economic opportunities.
    Diaries; Black studies; Population; Family planning; Social sciences; Segregation; United States; Switzerland
  - 1966 January 3-June 14, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 278 pages (Box 122, Reel M Dev 6, Frame 766)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney attends the Conference on Business Managers of Predominantly Negro colleges, the Meeting on the Race and Education Project and the White House Conference. He also travels to various universities to assess their summer preparatory programs for underprivileged and minority students.
    Civil rights; Education; Minorities; Social sciences; United States; Diaries
  - 1966 June 15-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 307 pages (Reel M Dev 7, Frame 1, Box 122)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits various colleges and universities in the United States to assess their programs catering to minority and underprivileged students.
    Education; Minorities; Social sciences; United States; Diaries
  - 1967 January 3-April 29, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 266 pages (Box 123, Reel M Dev 7, Frame 311)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits various southern universities and colleges to talk about integration of private colleges. He visits the Atlanta University Center to assess their academic programs and attends various conferences on the improvement of minority education and population studies.
    United States; Social sciences; Diaries; Economics; Education; Minorities; Population
  - 1967 May 1-September 29, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 278 pages (Reel M Dev 7, Frame 579, Box 123)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits various institutions around the country to see various projects underway to bridge educational and economic gap with disadvantaged and minority students.
    African Americans -- Education; Minorities; Mexican Americans; Diaries; Education; Economics; United States; Social sciences; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Population
  - 1967 October 2-December 21, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 196 pages (Reel M Dev 7, Frame 857, Box 123)
    Diaries; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Social sciences; Minorities; Population; United States; Education; Economics; African Americans -- Education
  - 1968 January 4-April 30, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 243 pages (Reel M Dev 8, Frame 1, Box 123)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. The topic of bridging educational gap at the college level with minority and underprivileged students is discussed at length. Varying views on black nationalism are noted from professionals in the field in terms of the effect on higher education student bodies.
    Black militant organizations; African Americans -- Education; United States; Education; Social sciences; Diaries
  - 1968 May 1-September 27, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 260 pages (Reel M Dev 8, Frame 250, Box 123)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. College, vocational and occupational preparatory programs are discussed at length for underprivileged and minority students as well as the changing roles of public educational professionals. DeVinney attends the Chicago Urban League Conference and the Educational Leadership Conference.
    Diaries; United States; African Americans -- Education; Education; Social sciences
  - 1968 October 1-December 30, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 184 pages (Reel M Dev 8, Frame 516, Box 123)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits Atlanta University Center and the Third Annual Convention of the National Community School Education Association.
    Diaries; African Americans -- Education; Social sciences; United States; Education
  - 1969 January 2-May 29, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 295 pages (Reel M Dev 8, Frame 701, Box 124)
    United States; Minorities; Population; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Social sciences; African Americans -- Education; Education; Diaries
  - 1969 June 2-December, DeVinney, Leland C.; Rockefeller Foundation; 271 pages (Box 124, Reel M Dev 9, Frame 1)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits various institutions around the country to see various projects underway to bridge educational and economic gap with disadvantaged and minority students. DeVinney also attends the Conference on National Programs for Infant and Preschool Childcare at Villa Serbelloni in Italy.
    African Americans -- Education; Early childhood education; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Diaries; Population; United States; Social sciences; Education; Economics; Minorities; Italy
  - 1970 January 5-July 20, DeVinney, Leland C.; Rockefeller Foundation; 280 pages (Reel M Dev 9, Frame 274, Box 124)
    Minorities; Education; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Population; African-American studies; African Americans -- Education; Economics; Diaries; Social sciences; United States
  - 1970 August 20-December 31, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 212 pages (Reel M Dev 9, Frame 558, Box 124)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits Atlanta University Center, Benedict College, Locke High School, Saugus Residential Educational Center and California State College at Los Angeles to assess RF grants. Integration of inner urban public schools is discussed as well in this diary.
    United States; Poverty -- Economic conditions; Social sciences; Education; Minorities; Economics; African Americans -- Education; African-American studies; Diaries
  - 1971 January 6-May 28, Rockefeller Foundation; DeVinney, Leland C.; 192 pages (Reel M Dev 9, Frame 773, Box 124)
    Organized according to interview and visit, DeVinney discusses projects and proposals with professionals in the field of social science. The documented interviews describe the background of the interviewee, their current research and Devinney's thoughts or actions on whether or not these proposals would be acceptable RF research grant projects. He is involved in the progress of the RF programs, development of new projects and financing current and future research. DeVinney visits Howard University, University of Miami and Los Angeles to determine quality of grant project proposals for the Rockefeller Foundation.
    United States; Education; Social sciences; Diaries
- Dick, George Williamson A.
  - 1946-1948 (Box 125)
- Dinning, James S.
  - 1963-1969 (Box 125)
  - 1970-1974 (Box 125)
- Downs, Wilbur G.
  Wilbur George Downs was a naturalist and virologist. Born in Perth Amboy, New Jersey, he received his B.A. and M.D. from Cornell University.
  Downs' professional career began as a Field Staff Member for a New York biological survey. He then held an internship and residency at the New York Hospital before serving as First Lieutenant with the AUS in Trinidad. Next, Downs travelled to the South Pacific and Bougainville as a Malaria Control Officer and later to Okinawa, Japan as Lieutenant Colonel, Malaria Control Officer of the Preventative Medicine. Downs remained in Okinawa as the Acting Chief of Preventative Medicine until 1946, when he retired from the army. Back in America, Downs became a professor of epidemiology at Yale Medical School and subsequently assumed the role of clinical professor. In 1964, Downs was the recipient of an honorary M.A. from Yale University. Throughout his military career, Downs also worked extensively for the Rockefeller Foundation. Beginning in 1940, Downs received a fellowship from the International Health Division, which enabled him to acquire a M.P.H. from Johns Hopkins School of Hygiene and Public Health. He worked on the Epidemiological Survey of Malaria in Trinidad and Tobago before being assigned to Mexico as a Malaria Control Researcher. In Mexico, he was among the first to question the use of insecticides like DDT in trying to control the disease. From 1946 to 1952, Downs was the Director of the Public Health and Malaria Investigation Program of the International Health Division in Mexico. In 1952, Dr. Downs was asked by the Rockefeller Foundation to establish a program in Trinidad investigating arthropod-borne viruses. He founded the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory, now the Caribbean Epidemiology Center in Port-of-Spain. Here, Downs trained numerous arbovirologists and was part of a team that isolated and characterized more than thirty-five new viruses. Downs continued his career as the Associate Director for the Medical and Natural Sciences Division until 1964 when he became the Director of the Medical and Natural Sciences Virus Program. Between 1961 and 1991, Wilbur George Downs was the Director and subsequently, an Administrator, for the Yale Arbor Virus Research Unit. Downs served as a member for multiple scientific committees and societies during his career. He was a consultant to projects in the Caribbean, Asia and Africa, and a member or chairman of advisory committees for the World Health Organization, the United States Public Health Service, the State Department, the Department of Defense and the National Academy of Sciences. Furthermore, he received a Bronze Star for his work in the military, the Richard M. Taylor Award (American Committee of Arthropod-Borne Viruses) and the Walter Reed Medal (ASTMH.)
  - 1941 July 16-1942 January 24, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 26 pages (Box 126, Reel M Dow 1, Frame 1)
    Entrusted with organizing a Malaria Control Program in Trinidad, Dr. Downs records his daily administrative duties, the creation of his laboratory, and the public health initiative that is introduced in Port of Spain. Entries record laboratory activities such as dissecting mosquitoes and identifying local strains of mosquitoes; clinical activities pertaining to the surveillance and treatment of malaria within the local population; and management activities related to the materials, staff, and funds needed to execute the program. During this time period Dr. Downs is stationed in Port of Spain, but also makes visits to neighboring Tobago to review other anti-malaria programs.
    DDT (Insecticide); Diaries; Trinidad; Public health; Prevention and health; Malaria; Epidemiology; Entomology
  - 1946 January 23-December 29, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 55 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 29, Box 126)
    Dr. Downs returns to Port of Spainafter his military tour during World War IIand reports upon the evolution of the anti-malaria programs in both Trinidad and Tobago since his departure. He discusses the slide diagnostic service, bromeliad spraying, and DDT-residual house spraying implemented by the new malaria offices, and makes visits to scientists and staff employed by malaria control programs. After a brief trip to Bogota, Colombia, Dr. Downs leaves Port of Spain and reports to Mexico City in order to assume his new position as head of the Mexican malaria control program: which is already dually funded by the Rockefeller Foundation and the Mexican Government. Entries record the various public health departments, institutes, hospitals, and laboratories that he visits, as well as all staff both government and privately employedwith whom he consults on matters regarding malaria and other endemic diseases. Scientific progress and data tables of the malaria control programs are embedded within the text and include frequent updates on the spleen rates of school children surveyed for infection by the malaria parasite.
    Trinidad; Public health; Prevention and health; Mexico; Diaries; Malaria; Epidemiology; Entomology; DDT (Insecticide)
  - 1946 December 30-1948 January 3, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 145 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 84, Box 126)
    As the head of the "Oficina de Especializacion Sanitaria" in Mexico City, Dr. Downs reports daily on the nature of his administrative duties and the development of his scientific investigations. Weekly fieldtrips to Mexican institutes, hospitals, and health centers yield entries on the progress and state of anti-malaria programs across the country. In regards to his scientific work, Dr. Downs includes the results of research conducted on the retention of DDT residual spraying on adobe surfaces; the progress of research associated with the colonies of mosquitoes maintained at the three collecting stations in Xochimilco (maps and schematics of the collecting stations are included); and the process used to identify breeding grounds. Clinical work also continues as Dr. Downs examines schoolchildren for malaria infection records. Final figures of spleen rates are found both within the entries and in a weekly log. Updates on the progress of regional and country-to country DDT spraying are documented as well.
    Public health; Diaries; Arboviruses; DDT (Insecticide); Entomology; Epidemiology; Malaria; Mexico; Prevention and health
  - 1948 January 5-December 25, Rockefeller Foundation; Downs, Wilbur G.; 139 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 234, Box 126)
    Dr. Downs continues with office, field, and laboratory work associated with the Oficina de Especializacion Sanitaria in Mexico. He discusses the establishment of regional training centers, as well as the staff involved, and makes various field trips to programs beings developed to combat malaria and other infectious diseases. Entries describe the results of clinical surveys recording spleen rates among schoolchildren and discuss scientific progress related to laboratory work on malaria. The progress of DDT spraying and the DDT analysis program are described and recorded in detail.
    Diaries; Arboviruses; DDT (Insecticide); Entomology; Epidemiology; Malaria; Mexico; Public health; Prevention and health
  - 1948 December 27-1949 December 31, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 127 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 373, Box 126)
    In an effort to allow planning of more effective and economical malaria control, Dr. Downs devotes much of his time to the establishment of an insectary at Acatlipa, Mexico. There, he works in collaboration with Sr. Bordaswho writes three weeks of diary entries for this periodto ensure the maintenance and propagation of four mosquito species to be used in experimental analysis of DDT. Observations of the mosquitoes are recorded on a daily basis and experiments testing the retention of DDT residual spraying on adobe bricks are emphasized. The distribution of anti-malaria supplies continues as well. Children are examined in order to identify malarious towns and town topography is surveyed to identify mosquito breeding grounds. Based on such observations, Dr. Downs recommends either anti-larval supplies or DDT for malaria control. Dr. Downs frequently addresses public health economics and the cost of supplies as the RF initiative begins to hold local towns responsible for funding their own anti-malaria supplies.
    Prevention and health; Diaries; Mexico; Public health; DDT (Insecticide); Arboviruses; Entomology; Malaria; Epidemiology
  - 1950, Downs, Wilbur G.; Rockefeller Foundation; 193 pages (Reel M Dow 1, Frame 544, Box 126)